[
    {
        "course": "economics",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "<p> (a) Explain each of the following measures of central tendency</p><p>(i) mean;<br>\n(ii) median;<br>\n(iii) mode<br>\n(b) Calculate the mean, median and mode of the following set of numbers: 21, 22, 23,24, 25, 26, 23, 28, 29, 30, 24, 31, 34, 23</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) Means is the average of a series of figures or values. It is obtained by dividing the sum of these figures by the total number of the figures or values. It is also the average of a collection of observation.</p><p>(ii) The median is an average which is the middle value when figures are arranged in order of magnitude. In an even distribution the median is the average of the two middle numbers.</p><p>(iii) Mode is a measure of central tendency. It tells us the observation which is most popular, that is, the most frequently occurring value in a distribution. From the following observations 1, 3, 4, 3, 5, 3, mode is 3</p><p>(b) Mean = \\(\\frac{21 +22+23+23+23+24+24+25+26+27+28+29+30+31+34} {15}\\) </p><p>= \\(\\frac{390} {15}\\) =26</p><p>median: 21, 22, 23, 23, 23, 24, 24, <ins><strong> 25 </strong></ins> 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 34, = 25</p><p>Mode = 23</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "economics",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "<p>What are the factors that determine the price elasticity of demand for a commodity? </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>Factors that determine the price elasticity of demand for a commodity are:<br>\n(i)The consumer's income: </strong>The higher the consumers income, the more inelastic his demand for goods and services will tend to be.</p><p><strong>(ii) Substitutes: </strong>Commodities which have close substitutes tend to have a high price elasticity of demand while those that do not have close substitutes are likely to be inelastic.</p><p><strong>(iii) Nature of commodity:</strong> Whether the commodity is a necessary or a luxury good will affect the elasticity of demand. Any good that is considered necessary will always be demanded even if the price is increased, i.e, the good is inelastic in demand. Luxury goods on the other hand are highly elastic in demand.</p><p><strong>(iv) One's habit: </strong>When one forms a habit on the consumption of a commodity a change in the price of that commodity will not affect one's demand for such commodity.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "economics",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "<p> What are the likely reasons for government participation in the location of industries in Nigeria? </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong> Likely reasons for government participation in the location of industries in Nigeria are as follows: </strong></p><p>(i) To raise the people's standard of living</p><p>(ii) to ensure that standard goods are produced locally</p><p>(iii) to make sure that industries are scattered all over the country for even development</p><p>(iv) political consideration</p><p>(v) to provide employment opportunities</p><p>(vi) to bridge rural-urban political imbalance</p><p>(vii) Another reason for government participation is income distribution in a country. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "economics",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "<p> What functions do wholesalers perform for manufacturers? </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>Functions of wholesalers to the manufacturers are: </strong></p><p>(i) The wholesalers provides warehousing facilities to get rid of stockpiling at the production point. Goods are stored here until! they are bought, hence it assures the manufacturers to keep on producing</p><p>(ii)The wholesaler purchases goods in bulk from the producer.</p><p>(iii) Provision of information to the producer regarding the retailers' and customers' views about the products. The views concern change in taste, fashion and defects.</p><p>(iv) They finance production by making prompt payment to the producer.</p><p>(v) The wholesaler sometimes brand and package goods from the producers before selling to the retailers.</p><p>(vi) <strong>Provision of transport: </strong>The wholesalers often provide transport needed in distribution. They send their vehicles to collect the goods from the manufacturers.</p><p>(vii) <strong>Advertisement</strong>: They help in carrying out such marketing functions as advertising, packaging and displaying of the products in strategic locations.</p><p>(viii) The wholesaler can give credit facilities to the manufacturers. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "economics",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "<p>Explain each of the following types of taxes:<br>\n(a) Proportional tax;<br>\n(b) progressive tax;<br>\n(c) regressive tax.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)Proportional tax:</strong> The rate of tax is the same , irrespective of the level of income. If a tax leads to both the rich and the poor paying the same proportion or percentage of their incomes as tax, then the tax is called proportional tax.</p><p><strong>(b) Progressive tax: </strong>This is a form of tax in which tax rate increases as income increases. It takes a larger percentage of income from people with larger incomes. A progressive tax reduces inequality of income distribution. A good example is the PAYE.</p><p><strong>(c) Regressive tax: </strong>The higher the income, the lower is the rate of tax. It is a tax system where tax rate decreases as income increase. In this type of taxation, a poor person pays a higher proportion of his income, e.g, poll tax. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "economics",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "<p>Outline the merits of a Joint Stock Company. </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>Merits of a joint stock company are: </strong><br>\n(i) There is a perpetual existence because the death of any shareholder does not affect the business.</p><p>(ii) It has enough capital to engage specialists.</p><p>(iii) Joint stock company operates on a large scale and therefore enjoys the economies of large scale.</p><p>(iv) The company enjoys limited liability. The shareholders' liability is limited to the amount of shares held or agreed to purchase.</p><p>(v) It is a separate legal entity: It can sue and be sued as a corporate body.</p><p>(vi) The company can raise large capital by offering shares to the public.</p><p>(vii) It can easily raise loans, e.g debentures.</p><p>(viii) There is no limit to expansion.</p><p>(ix) There is democracy in its management: Shareholders are entitled to attend the annual general meeting and in the election of members of board of directors they have equal right to vote and be voted for.</p><p>(x) There is greater opportunity to undertake research programmes. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "economics",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "<p>Highlight the economic effects of high population density in Nigeria. </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>Economic effects of high population density on Nigeria are: </strong></p><p>(I) There will be a lot of pressure on the existing social amenities, e.g. schools, roads, pipe borne water.</p><p>(ii) There will be increase in the level of unemployment.</p><p>(iii) The standard of living of the people will fall as a result of a fall in per capita income.</p><p>(iv) The crime rate will increase tremendously as in Lagos.</p><p>(v) High population density will lead to congestion in the areas of traffic, housing and schools.</p><p>(vi) There will be high demand for goods and services which may lead to shortage.</p><p>(vii) There will be increase in the dependency ratio. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "economics",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "<p> How does the Central Bank exercise control over commercial banks?</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>The Central Bank exercises control over commercial banks in the following ways: </strong><br>\n<strong>(i) Open market operation:</strong> The Central bank applies open market operations with a view to regulating the volume of money in circulation. By this operation, the central bank purchases or sells government securities to the commercial banks.</p><p><strong>(ii) Special directives: </strong>This is issued to commercial banks to restrict or liberalize their loan policy to business men.</p><p><strong>(iii) Bank rate: </strong>The bank rate is the rate of interest charged by the central bank for discounting bills. The Central Bank controls the commercial banks by raising or lowering the bank rate as the need arises.</p><p><strong>(iv) Moral suasion: </strong>The Central Bank sometimes engages in friendly dialogue with the other banks in order to agree on how banking activities are to be carried out. It is a gentle appeal made by the central bank to the commercial banks to restrict their expansion of credit to the public and to be selective in their lending operations.</p><p><strong>(v) Cash ratio: </strong>The commercial banks are required by law to keep a specified proportion of their total deposits with the Central Bank in the form of bank reserves, usually 25% of their total deposits. The size of the reserve can be raised or lowered according to the economic exigencies of the country.</p><p><strong>(vi) Special deposits: </strong>The Central Bank has the right to require the other banks to make special deposits with it. This type of forced deposits has the effect of limiting the liquid cash available to the banks for other operations.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "economics",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "<p>Describe the problems facing agriculture in Nigeria.<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong> Problems facing agriculture in Nigeria are: </strong></p><p><strong>(i)Unsuitable climatic conditions:</strong> Climatic conditions vary from areas of excessive rainfall to areas of excessive drought. These two types of climatic conditions are detrimental to crop and animal growth.</p><p><strong>(ii) Poor technical knowledge:</strong> The farmers lack requisite technical knowledge and modern skills to raise the standard of farming and agricultural production in their countries.</p><p><strong>(iii) Use of crude implements:</strong> West African farmers still use crude implements such as cutlass, hoes etc for farming. They have no opportunity for mechanized farming.</p><p><strong>(iv) Rural- urban drift:</strong> The imbalance in urban-rural economy has led to rural -urban drift. Agriculture has thus been losing its vital labour force without replacing it with mechanization.</p><p><strong>(v) Land tenure system: </strong>Land tenure system encourages small scale farming. Modern agriculture is difficult under the existing land tenure system which makes transfer of ownership of land extremely difficult.</p><p><strong>(vi) Pest and diseases: </strong>They reduce the quality and quantity of agricultural products since farmers cannot afford to purchase insecticides.</p><p><strong>(vii) Poor marketing facilities:</strong> The sale of products is limited to their immediate environment because of poor transportation and communication systems.</p><p><strong>(viii) Inadequate finance: </strong>Consequent on the low income earnings of the farmers, savings and realization of capital for investment become almost impossible. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "economics",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "<p>Cost schedule of a firm </p><table border=\"1\" cellpadding=\"0\" cellspacing=\"0\" style=\"width:100%\">\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>Output</td>\n<td>Total Fixed cost TFC(N)</td>\n<td>Total Variable Cost TVC (N)</td>\n<td>Total Cost  TC (N)</td>\n<td>Average Variable AVC(N)</td>\n<td>Average Total ATC (N)</td>\n<td>Marginal Cost MC(N)</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>0</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>0</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>0</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>-</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>1</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>40</td>\n<td>140</td>\n<td>-</td>\n<td>-</td>\n<td>-</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>2</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>64</td>\n<td>164</td>\n<td>-</td>\n<td>-</td>\n<td>-</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>3</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>80</td>\n<td>180</td>\n<td>-</td>\n<td>-</td>\n<td>-</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>4</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>88</td>\n<td>188</td>\n<td>-</td>\n<td>-</td>\n<td>-</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>5</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>96</td>\n<td>196</td>\n<td>-</td>\n<td>-</td>\n<td>-</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><p>From the cost schedule in this table calculate the Average Variable Cost (AVC), Average Total Cost (ATC) and Marginal Cost (MC) of the firm. Show your working clearly.<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<table border=\"1\" cellpadding=\"0\" cellspacing=\"0\" style=\"width:100%\">\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>Output</td>\n<td>TFC(N)</td>\n<td> TVC (N)</td>\n<td> TC (N)</td>\n<td>AVC(N)</td>\n<td>ATC (N)</td>\n<td>MC(N)</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>0</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>0</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>0</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>-</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>1</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>40</td>\n<td>140</td>\n<td>40</td>\n<td>140</td>\n<td>40</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>2</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>64</td>\n<td>164</td>\n<td>32</td>\n<td>82</td>\n<td>24</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>3</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>80</td>\n<td>180</td>\n<td>27</td>\n<td>60</td>\n<td>16</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>4</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>88</td>\n<td>188</td>\n<td>22</td>\n<td>47</td>\n<td>8</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>5</td>\n<td>100</td>\n<td>96</td>\n<td>196</td>\n<td>19.2</td>\n<td>39.2</td>\n<td>8</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><p> </p><p>AVC = \\(\\frac{TVC}{Q}\\) = 40, 32, 27, 22, 19.2</p><p>ATC = \\(\\frac{TVC}{39.2}\\) = 140, 82, 60,47,</p><p>MC = TC, TC2 = 40 , 24, 16, 8, 8 <br>\n </p><p> </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]